Joel Pinheiro

Software Engineer

joelpinheiro.github.io | +351 910 399 321 | joelcoelhopinheiro@gmail.com

Summary

Hello, I'm a **Software Engineer** from Porto, Portugal. I'm currently **working in BNP Paribas** at Brussels as **Java Developer**. I spend most of my time **crafting** and **working** on awesome projects. I define myself as a **full stack engineer** with know how with software **architecture**, **scalability** and **performance**. I am able to adapt to **multicultural environments**, gained through working **experience abroad** (Netherlands and Belgium). My main interests are **Security**, **Big Data, Machine Learning**, **Finance** and **Web**. I'm currently available to take part in some **interesting smaller projects**.

Work History

Software Engineer

Sep 2016 - Now

Consultant @ ING Bank & BNP Paribas (Brussels)

Project: Online Leasing Solution & Reporting Tool. **Technologies**: Java 8, Spring Boot, Spring Security, GWT, Hibernate/JPA, JavaScript (ECMA5), Unit/Integration Tests, Maven, Nexus, Jenkins, Git + GitLab.

Researcher Apr 2015 - Jan 2016

Instituto de Telecomunicações

Project: IoT Decentralised Framework. **Technologies**: JavaScript (ECMA 5 / 6), TypeScript, HTML5 tools such as WebRTC, web threads (WebWorkers), UnitTests, Gulp.

Software Engineer

2014 - 2014

2009 - 2011

FIS, Amsterdam (Netherlands)

Project: Online Banking Solution for Harrods Bank. **Technologies**: Java Enterprise (Struts, Spring), Tomcat, GTM Database and Web Development.

Java Developer

CA Informática - Credito Agricola, Lisbon (Portugal)

Application: Calypso (financial solution - Java Web Start Application) Projects: Foreign Exchange, Bonds, Bloomberg Interface **Technologies**: Java, Oracle Database 10g, Microsoft Visual SourceSafe, WSDL.

Education

Bachelor & Master's in Computer and Telematics Engineering

2011 - 2016

University of Aveiro

Favorite Courses: Operating Systems, Algorithms And Complexity, Programming I-III, Computer Architecture, Data Bases, Network Architecture, Security, Distributed Systems, Concurrent Programming and Audio And Video Coding.

Projects Portfolio / Open Source Software

iTrading (Side Project): joelpinheiro.github.io/itrading

Github Repository: github.com/joelpinheiro



Skills

Java

Six years of experience. Three years of enterprise level experience and three more in university. This is the language I feel most comfortable to use in order to solve any problem. Currently studying to be a Java 8 certified developer.

Javascript

Two years of experience. Highly used on professional/academic projects.

Python

One year of experience. Academic experience and some side projects. Take a look at Projects Portfolio section.

C/C++

Academic experience. Take a look at Projects Portfolio section.

Scala

Currently doing the Martin Odersky' Scala

specialisation of Coursera.

Techs/Frameworks

NodeJS, Spring, GWT, CherryPy, Atom Shell (Electron), JAX-RS/Jetty, Express, Socket.io, Django, Angular.JS, JQuery, Meteor.JS, D3, Hibernate/JPA.

Tools

Docker, NGINX, Chef, Vagrant, Puppet, Ansible, Jenkins, Maven.

Certifications

- Java SE 8 Oracle Certified Professional
- **Scrum Master** Accredited Certification by Scrum Institute
- **Principles of functional programming** in **Scala** by Martin Odersky (Coursera)